A Finding Aid to the Glen Kaufman Papers, 1957-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.kaufglen
Archives of American Art
Glen Kaufman papers
1957-2011
AAA.kaufglen
Archives of American Art
1.1 Linear feet
The papers of fiber artist and educator Glen Kaufman measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1957-2011. The papers primarily document his travels and student work through biographical material, journals, printed materials and artwork. Included are 15 travel journals, two handwoven knotted pile rug samples, and two sketchbooks.
Kaufman, Glen
Biographical/Historical note
Glen Kaufman (1932- ) is a textile artist who lives and works in Athens, Georgia and Kyoto, Japan. He was also a Professor of Art at the University of Georgia, Athens from 1967-2008.
After graduating with honors from the University of Wisconsin-Madison, Kaufman went on to attend the Cranbrook Academy of Art in Michigan and to obtain his MFA in 1959. The following year he attended the State School of Arts and Crafts in Copenhagen, Denmark on a Fulbright Grant.
In 1967 he began teaching fiber arts at the University of Georgia in Athens, Georgia where he continued teaching until 2008. In 1979 he traveled extensively throughout Asia and became enamored with Japan and their fiber arts traditions. By 1985 he was spending six months every year in Japan where he continued to work and show his art. His work from this time was heavily influenced by Japanese motifs such as the grid, which was predominately featured in his pieces. He continues to produce fiber art and display his work today in places such as the Lyndon House Arts Center in Athens, Georgia where he recently held an exhibition entitled “Kaunakes: Ghosts of Mesopotamia” in 2011.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Glen Kaufman in 2012.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 4 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1957-2011 (5 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Travel Journals, 1987-1993 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 1-2)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1976-2011 (5 folders; Box 2)
Series 4: Artwork, 1958-circa 1974 (0.4 linear feet; Boxes 2-3)
Scope and Contents note
The papers of fiber artist and educator Glen Kaufman measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1957-2011. The papers primarily document his travels and student work through biographical material, journals, printed materials and artwork. Included are 15 travel journals, two handwoven knotted pile rug samples, and two sketchbooks.
Fiber artists--Georgia; Fiber artists--Japan; Sketchbooks; Travel journals
- Biographical Material, 1957-2011; Series 1; 5 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are a curriculum vitae, one electronic disc (DVD) of photos from an exhibit entitled “Kaunakes: Ghosts of Mesopotamia”, a notebook of student notes and project documents including fiber samples, slides of an exhibit, an invoice and cost sheet, and a research notebook containing notes and some drawings.
  Arrangement note
  Kaufman's graduate studies notebook was removed from the original binder and split into two folders. The original order of the documents was kept intact.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2011 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Photographs, "Kaunakes: Ghosts of Mesopotamia", 2011; Includes 1 electronic disc (DVD). (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Notebook, Graduate Studies Cranbrook Academy of Art, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, Studies State School of Arts and Crafts, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Research Notebook on Historic Fabrics, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Travel Journals, 1987-1993; Series 2; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Found here are accounts of the artist’s time spent in Japan for roughly six months per year including thoughts, daily activities, people he spent time with, shows he saw, his own work, and travel within Asia. Also included is one journal specific to his time spent in Malaysia though it only appears to contain a few entries.
  Original chronological order of notebooks was maintained and the volume numbers were assigned by Kaufman.
  - Japan Journal, vol. I, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Japan Journal, vol. I, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Japan Journal, vol. I, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Japan Journal, vol. I, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Japan Journal, vol. III, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Japan Journal, vol. I, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Japan Journal, vol. I, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Malaysia Journal, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II and I, 1992-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Japan Journal, vol. II, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Printed Material, 1976-2011; Series 3; 5 Folders Box 2
  Printed material consists of exhibition flyers and a newspaper clipping regarding his show, “Kaunakes: Ghosts of Mesopotamia”; an American Craft magazine in which the artist is featured on page 40; an annotated book of maps of London; and an annotated directory of the Royal College of Art from when the artist was a guest lecturer in 1976.
  - Exhibition Flyers, "Kaunakes: Ghosts of Mesopotamia", 2011 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clipping, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - American Craft Magazine, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - London Guide, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Directory, Royal College of Art, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Artwork, 1958-circa 1974; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 2-3
  Found here are samples of two of the artist’s handwoven, knotted pile rugs made while a graduate student at Cranbrook Academy of Art. Researchers should note that sketches of these works can be found in Kaufman’s graduate studies notebook in Series 1: Biographical Material. There are also two sketchbooks, the first of which contained sketches in preparation for a solo show and the second, from his time studying in Copenhagen at the State School of Arts and Crafts.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1974 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Sketchbook, State School of Arts and Crafts, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Handwoven Knotted Pile Rug Sample, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Handwoven Knotted Pile Rug Sample, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 3)